<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- $Id: debian-i18n-l10n.xml,v 1.11 2007-08-26 18:09:48 bubulle Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/dtd/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- TODO (generic)

   - Talk about generic l10n frameworks?
   - Collaboration with Ubuntu? (translations are not synched back to Debian)
   - Review TODOs and FIXMEs :-)
   - Talk about things we cannot l10n? Like sysvinit scripts 
-->

<!-- TODO, review these sources

 * http://people.debian.org/~bubulle/debconf4/

 * http://www.perrier.eu.org/debian/talks/debconf5/tutorial-l10n/

 * http://people.debian.org/~debacle/linuxtag2005debianday/luk_claes-i18n_and_l10n.pdf

 * http://people.debian.org/~luk/i18n-l10n.pdf

 * http://es.tldp.org/Articulos/0000otras/doc-traduccion-libre/doc-traduccion-libre/ (Spanish)

 * http://www.debian.org.es/debconf-es2/charlas/i18n.pdf (Spanish)

 * http://people.debian.org/~lwall/i18n/ (po-debconf status)

 * http://people.debian.org/~bubulle/d-i/i18n-doc/
 (sources at http://people.debian.org/~seppy/d-i/d-i-i18n-documentation/)
 

-->

<book>
  <title>Internationalisation and localisation in Debian</title>
  <titleabbrev>Debian i18n-l10n</titleabbrev>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Internationalisation and localisation in Debian</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Javier</firstname> <surname>Fern&aacute;ndez-Sanguino
	Pe&ntilde;a</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<orgname>The Debian Project</orgname>
	<address><email>jfs@debian.org</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <firstname>Christian</firstname> <surname>Perrier</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<orgname>The Debian Project</orgname>
	<address><email>bubulle@debian.org</email></address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    
    <date>March 2006</date>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year>
      <holder>Authors: Christian Perrier, Javier Fern&aacute;ndez-Sanguino</holder>
    </copyright>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year>
      <holder>Reviewers: Clytie Siddall, MJ Ray</holder>
    </copyright>
    <copyright>
      <year>2007</year>
      <holder>Reviewer: Y Giridhar Appaji Nag</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
        This book is distributed under the terms and conditions of GPL
        version 2 or later.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <abstract>
      <para>
	Debian is one of the most ambitious free software
	projects, putting together a large number of developers from
	all around the world working in building a free operating
	system.
      </para>
      <para>This document describes the rationale and management of internationalisation
      and localisation within the Debian project, including the
      current infrastructure and tools available to both translators and
      package maintainers.
      </para>
      <para>
       Keywords: free software, translation, internationalisation,
       localisation, operating system
      </para>
    </abstract>

  </bookinfo>


  <chapter id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The following document describes the approach taken for
    handling internationalisation and localisation in the Debian
    project describing the infrastructure, and tools available for
    translators and package maintainers as well as the work done by
    the different translation team members.</para>

    <section><title>English as the official language?</title>

       <para>English is often regarded as the official language of most free
       software projects. This assumption affects users of free software and
       users of information systems generally, to the degree that "They
       should all just speak English!" is a frequent reaction to
       internationalisation projects. On behalf of the majority of the
       world's population - who do not speak English - a great deal of work
       is done voluntarily in the Debian project, to ensure that program
       interfaces do not only present their messages in English and that
       most documentation is not only written in English.</para>

       <para>Currently, most of the working groups within Debian use English as
       their main language for information exchange (discussions,
       documentation, etc.). Developers, even if not native speakers, program
       code with an English interface and write documentation in English. The
       main information sources of official documentation  (including the
       project website) are first written in English.</para>

       <para>A single working language helps coordinate work
       of multiple developers worldwide, and helps people exchange their ideas.
       English is the common language for <ulink
       url="http://www.debian.org/contact.en.html">communication with Debian
       developers</ulink>. However, using only English disadvantages many
       potential users and limits the pool of potential
       developers. It's an accessibility issue, as well as a usability
       issue. We want everyone to be able to use their computer effectively,
       regardless of the languages they are familiar with or can understand,
       and that's what internationalisation is about.</para>

    </section>

    <section><title>The importance of internationalisation and localisation</title>

    <para>Debian's goal of providing a <emphasis>universal</emphasis>
    operating system is based on the voluntary work of many translation
    teams. Having a <emphasis>universal</emphasis> operating system
    does not only mean having all possible software tools available,
    it also means providing an operating system that can be used by
    anyone worldwide. Even though English is a very widely-used language in
    the IT world today, this does not mean that all the world population can
    speak it, or even understand it. As we have pointed out, in fact, the
    majority of the world's population cannot use English. That is why this
    goal is so important and why we need to fulfill it, at least partly, by
    providing an operating system accessible to every user, in a language they
    are familiar with, regardless of what that language is. The more languages
    we support, the more people we reach. It's as simple as that.  </para>

    <para>This means Debian needs to provide an installation system
    that can also be used by non-English speakers, and that can set up a
    system also suitable for use for non-English speakers. Debian users
    need to be able to read about the operating system itself,
    itself, so documentation must be translated, as well as application
    interfaces. Both the documentation available in the
    operating system itself, and the documentation available through
    other sources (e.g. the project's website). Debian users need to be
    able to ask for help, so mailing lists, IRC channels, fora and other
    interactive help systems need be available to them in a language they can
    use.</para>

    <para>Making Debian usable by more people is also a selfish goal
    for the project: having more users means that the software
    developed by the project gets used more (more exposure leads to
    more testing and eventually, more features) and it also
    means that the new users might eventually contribute to the
    project (through bug reports, patches, translations) and even
    become Debian developers themselves. More access simply means more
    resources.</para>


    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The internationalisation and localisation process</title>

      <para>According to <ulink
      url="http://www.debian.org/doc/manuals/intro-i18n">Introduction
      to i18n</ulink> from Tomohiro KUBOTA: <quote>I18N
      (internationalisation) means modification of a software or
      related technologies so that a software can potentially handle
      multiple languages, customs, and so on in the world.</quote> while
      <quote>L10N (localisation) means implementation of a specific language
      for an already internationalised software.</quote></para>

      <para>Internationalisation is the process that makes a program
      capable of providing a computing environment for the user adapted
      to his/her own language, currency, date and time formats, etc. Most
      users of a similar background will share an environment, and this
      means there a number of common environments that a
      program has to support. The term internationalisation is often
      abbreviated to i18n.</para>

      <para>Even if a piece of software is ready to use different
      environments, that does not mean that it can immediately do so, since
      specialists (typically people who use that environment) need to adapt it so
      that it can be used in a language a user is familiar with. This process
      of adapting the software to a specific environment is called
      localisation. Localisation is typically focused on the translation of
      each and every message that the program can handle (and implements in
      the user interface, such as menus, buttons, error messages and tooltips).
      Localisation is typically abbreviated to l10n.</para>

      <para>L10n and I18n are closely related, but the issues in
      achieving each of them are very different. It's not really difficult to
      allow the program to change the language in which texts are
      displayed, based on user settings, but it is very time consuming indeed,
      actually to translate all its messages. On the other hand, setting
      the character encoding may be trivial, but adapting the code to use
      several character encodings can be a challenging and complex task.</para>

      <para>This document will not try to explain all the different issues
      facing localisation and associated with the representation of different
      code pages. However, it's important to recognize that this is a key
      issue, especially for
      environments that do not use the Western code pages (ASCII character set
      and ISO-8859), such as Asian and Indic scripts and languages with
      combined diacritics. We need to bear in mind that the majority of
      potential users world-wide use languages which are not covered by those
      two very limited code pages. UTF-8 support is a crucial step in
      internationalization.</para>

 </section>

 <section>
 <title>Internationalising, translating and being internationalised and translated</title>

<!-- Written by Martin Quinson to the d-18n mailing list, may 2003 -->

  <para>Debian supports an ever-increasing number of 
  languages. Even if you are a native English speaker and do not speak
  any other language, it is part of your duty as a maintainer to be
  aware of issues of internationalisation.  Internationalisation is the bridge
  between you and most of your potential users. Therefore, even if you yourself
  can function effectively in English, this
  chapter gives you information you need as a maintainer.</para>

  <para>Like the overall i18n implementation, which still has to coalesce into
  a standard process, l10n within Debian does not yet have a central
  infrastructure which could be compared to the dbuild mechanism for porting.
  Currently, most of the work has to be done manually.</para>

<!-- TODO: adapt and link to the other parts of the text, this section serves as introduction -->
  <section>
  <title>How are translations managed within Debian?</title>

  <para>Handling translation of the texts contained in a package is
  still a manual task, and the process depends on the kind of text you
  want to see translated.</para>

  <para>For program messages, the gettext infrastructure is in common usage. For 
  applications the translation is handled upstream,
  within projects like the <ulink
  url="http://translationproject.org/">Translation
  Project</ulink>, <ulink
  url="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gtp/"> the Gnome
  Translation Project</ulink> or the <ulink
  url="http://i18n.kde.org/">KDE Translation Project</ulink>.  The
  only centralised l10n resource within Debian is the <ulink
  url="http://www.debian.org/intl/l10n/">overall Debian translation
  statistics</ulink>, where you can find information about the
  translation status of files found in an actual package. This is similar to
  <ulink url="http://i18n.redhat.com/cgi-bin/i18n-status">Fedora's Translation
  Status page</ulink>, but unfortunately different, at this stage, in that we
  don't yet have a common (unlike it) there is no common infrastructure to
  facilitate the translation process.</para>

  <para>An effort to translate the package descriptions started quite some time
  ago, even though very few tools currently support these translated descriptions (i.e.
  only APT can use them, when configured correctly). Maintainers do not need
  to do anything for this to work, and the translators should use
  the DDTP. For more information see <xref linkend="ddtp"/>.</para>

  <para>For debconf templates, maintainers should use the po-debconf
  package to help translators work more effectively. Some statistics of the
  integration of debconf translations in packages can be found on the
  <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/intl/l10n/">overall Debian
  translation statistics</ulink> pages. For more information, see <xref
  linkend="po-debconf"/></para>

  <para>For web pages, each l10n team has access to the appropiate CVS,
  and the statistics are available at the overall Debian translation
  statistics site. For more information see <xref linkend="web-l10n"/>.</para>

  <para>For general documentation about Debian, the process is more or
  less the same as for the web pages (the translators typically need
  access to the CVS or SVN repository holding the documentation files), but
  there is no statistics pages yet, except for a few specific projects.
  Central information is definitely needed. For more information see <xref
  linkend="doc-l10n"/>.</para>

  <para>For package-specific documentation (man pages, info documents,
  and information in other formats, like XML/Docbook, HTML and PDF), almost
  everything has yet to be done. The KDE and GNOME projects handles translation of their
  documentation in the same way
  as their program messages, but there is no specific way to handle
  translation of documentation in Debian project-wide<footnote><para>The
  Translation Project and GNU are curently running a pilot project on the
  manpage translation (and distribution) process which we may be able to
  implement.</para></footnote>. The translation of Debian-specific man pages
  was initially handled within the <ulink
  url="http://cvs.debian.org/manpages/?cvsroot=debian-doc">manpages
  module</ulink> of the DDP CVS repository, but in some packages, manpages are
  handled just like generic documentation. For more information on how manpages
  translations are handled, see <xref linkend="manpages-l10n"/>.</para>

  <!-- TODO:
  GNU info does not provide any infrastructure to display localised info pages.
  -->

</section>

<section><title>I18N &amp; L10N FAQ for maintainers</title>

<para>This is a list of issues that Debian package maintainers may
face concerning I18n and L10n. While reading this, keep in mind that
there is not yet any real consensus on those
points within Debian, and that they are simply helpful advice. If you have a
better solution to a given issue, or if you disagree on some points, feel free
to provide your feedback, so that this document can be enhanced.</para>

  <variablelist>
 
  <varlistentry><term>How do I get a given text translated?</term> <listitem><para>
For translate package description or debconf templates, you have do not need to
do anything at all. The DDTP infrastructure will send the translatable
descriptions volunteers, and process the resulting translations with no need
for you to interact. Addition of debconf templates is followed by translation
teams that will send you new translations for them through the Bug Tracking
System (you can contact debian-i18n, however, if you would like translations
before releasing a new package version).</para>

<para>For all other material (PO files for applications, man pages or other
documentation), the best solution is to make your text available somewhere on
the Internet, and ask the translators on the debian-i18n mailing list to
translate your file(s) into their different languages. The translation
team leaders, at least, are subscribed to this list, and they will take care of the
translation and of the quality-assurance processes. Once this is complete, your
translated material will be emailed to you.  You may receive queries about
context for specific points (inserting context in your document will always
ensure a better quality of translation), and get typo reports as a bonus
feature.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>How do I get a given translation reviewed?</term> <listitem><para>
From time to time, somebody might translate some texts included in your package
and will ask you to include it when you release. Understandably, you want to
know if this translation is up to standard. You don't want to be releasing a
campaign speech or a dirty limerick instead. Therefore, you can send the
document to the Debian l10n mailing list for that language, asking for a
review. Once that is complete, you can feel more confident in the quality of
that translation, and can include it in your package with pride. You may also
have introduced a new translator to that language team: a valuable resource for
Debian.</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>How do I get a given translation updated?</term> <listitem><para>
If you already have some translations of a given text, each time you update the
original, you should also politely ask the previous translator to update
his/her work, to bring that translation up to date with regard to the current
original text. Keep in mind that this task takes time, just as it took you time
to update the original: allow for at least one week to get your translation
updated, reviewed and returned.
</para>

<para>If the translator doesn't respond for some reason, please contact the
Debian l10n mailling list for that language. The team-leader should respond
promptly. If you don't hear back from the team, please email the Debian i18n
mailing list, so it can follow this up or provide alternate contacts for
the team.  If, somehow, the translation doesn't get done in time (and this is
rare, when you follow these procedures), don't forget to put a warning
<footnote><para>If the translation is managed through gettext you do not need
to do this as the gettext tools will prevent the user from seeing translations
that have not been updated.</para></footnote> in the translated document,
stating that the translation is outdated, so the reader should also refer to
the original document if possible.</para>

<para>You should avoid removing a translation completely, simply because it is
outdated. An old document is usually better than no document at all for many
users. Old translations might also include glossary information that might be
useful for future reviews and you never know when a new translator will use the
old translation to provide an updated translation (which is typically faster
than writting a new translation from scratch).</para>

</listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>How do I handle a bug report concerning a translation?</term> 
<listitem><para>
These reports should really go to the translation team, whose contact details
are shown in all PO file headers, and should be shown on all documentation.
It's a good idea to advise users to send any i18n bug reports straight to
language teams<footnote><para>Upstream users can add a link on their site, to
the Debian language teams listing to prevent getting these
mails</para></footnote>. When you do get them, please mark the bug as
"forwarded to upstream", and forward it both to the previous translator and to
his/her language team (using the corresponding debian-l10n-XXX mailing list).</para>

</listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>How can I (as a maintainer) help the translation effort?</term> 
<listitem><para> You can eliminate a lot of wasted effort, and confusion, by
organizing your end of the l10n process. Choose carefully what you want to
translate (Debconf messages are always translated, but you might want to have
additional items translated), and integrate translation with your release
schedule (of either packages or new upstream versions).  Allow for a string
freeze before a release or package upload: this gives translators time to
complete and review translations. Plan to request translations on the
debian-i18n mailing list, at a realistic point before release, then again when
you announce the string freeze. Communicate readily with debian-i18n and your
translation teams: keep the information flowing.</para>

<para>If you are the maintainer of a popular package which might get
translations after a release, you might get updated translations for upstream
content (program messages and documentation) as bug reports or see changes in
upstream's revision control system after you have uploaded a new version.
Instead of sitting on the translations waiting for upstream to add them and
making a release, you can make this translations available in the Debian
package inmediately. This ensures that Debian users will see the translations
as soon as they are available and it also boosts the morale of translators
which see that their work is made available to users. Translators might get
frustated if they send you updated translations for a package (even after
sending them to upstream or updated upstream's repository) and do not see them
being included in the Debian package until upstream decides to make a new
upstream release. Unlike patches for source code, which might introduce
regressions and instability, changes to PO files or new translated manpages do
not affect the program itself and can be safely added.</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</section>

<section><title>I18N &amp; L10N FAQ for translators</title>

<para>While reading this, please keep in mind that there is no general
procedure within Debian concerning those points, yet, and that in any case, the
most effective way to resolve any issue is to work with your language teams.
Language teams are set up to ensure an integrated approach to translation for
that language, and that integration includes interfacing with
developers.</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>How can I help the translation effort?</term>
<listitem><para>If you are able to join the translation effort, welcome! We
appreciate your effort. As a quick guide: decide what you want to translate,
make sure that nobody is already working on it (using your debian-l10n-XXX
mailing list), translate it, get it reviewed by other native speaker on your
l10n mailing list, and provide it to the maintainer of the package (see next
point). The Debian i18n web pages, especially the Translation HowTo, can give
you more information.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>How can I provide a translation for inclusion in a package?</term>
<listitem><para> Most importantly, make sure that your translation is correct
(by asking for review on your l10n mailing list) before providing it for
inclusion. It will save time for everyone, and avoid the chaos resulting in
having several versions of the same document in different bug reports.
Translation teams are capable of quality work, and that is the reputation we
want for Debian i18n.</para>

<para>The recommended way to submit translations is to file a regular bug against the
package, with the translation file attached. Make sure to use the 'PATCH' tag,
and to not use a gravity higher than 'wishlist', since lack of translations
doesn't actually prevent a program from running<footnote><para>It might,
however, prevent people from using it</para></footnote>. For more information please
read <xref linkend="l10n_bts"/>.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</section>

<section><title>Best current practice concerning l10n</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
As a maintainer, never edit the translations in any way (even to reformat  the
layout) without asking on the corresponding l10n mailing list. You  risk, for
example, breaking the encoding of the file by doing so. Moreover,  what you
consider as an error can be right (or even needed) in the given  language. Trust
the expertise of translators these areas. 
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> As a translator, if you find an error in the original text,
please report it (by sending in another bug report, also of "wishlist"
priority). Often, translators are the most attentive readers of a given text,
and if they don't report the errors they find, nobody will. Also, it makes your
job easier, if the original text is correct.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In any case, remember that the major issue with l10n is that it requires
several people to cooperate effectively, and that it is all too easy to start a
flamewar about small problems, because of a misunderstanding. Avoid
misunderstandings by being as clear as you can, using straight-forward language
(avoid idiom, for example) and not making assumptions.  If you do run into
difficulties, please ask for help on the corresponding l10n mailing list, on
debian-i18n, or even on debian-devel.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Essentially, cooperation can only be achieved through
<emphasis>mutual respect</emphasis>. We are all working hard in the same
project: we achieve so much more when we work together.</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

  </section>

 </section>


  </chapter>

  <chapter id="i18n_l10n_projects">
    <title>I18n/L10n projects in Debian</title>

  <para>Debian has different ongoing processes, to facilitate the
  internationalisation of the software it develops, as well as to assist
  translators in working on the localisation of content produced for Debian.
  This chapter explains the different i18n and l10n ongoing projects in Debian,
  and describes how they work.</para>

  <section id="web-l10n">
    <title>Translation of the Debian website</title>

    <para>A project website is so often used as the primary
    information source for both the users of a program, and for
    people who want to learn about it but don't use it
    yet. Information on a project's website is usually complementary to the
    documentation available through other means.
    This website information is also typically more up-to-date than the
    documentation provided when the software was installed, or the distribution
    media in which it provided was purchased.</para>

    <para>This gives the website some priority in the internationalisation and
    localisation process of a universal project. It's out there, it's current,
    and it's being viewed: so it is translate, to make it accessible to many
    more people. A website is a moving target for translation, requiring
    frequent updates, but it's a key access point for users (both existing and
    future).</para>

    <para>In order to present translated information to the user, the Debian
    project website uses <emphasis>Content Negotiation</emphasis>
    technology (more specifically, <ulink
    url="http://www.apache.org/docs/content-negotiation.html">Apache's
    content negotiation</ulink>) that is based on the user's web
    browser providing information on chosen languages
    (<emphasis>Preferred-Language</emphasis> HTTP header).  The user may set
    this language preference individually in the browser, or simply ask the
    browser to follow the system preferences. Content negotiation, in this
    case, means that the website software can present a copy of the content
    translated to the user's most effective language (if a translated copy is
    available). More information on content negotiation is available on the
    Debian website's <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/intro/cn">description of
    content negotiation</ulink>. Translated websites will typically include a
    "language bar" which shows in which languages that site is
    available.</para>

    <para>In this way, server administrators will manage both the original
    document (typically in English) and multiple translations of that document.
    Content negotiation takes care of the task of looking for the document for
    a given URL in the nominated language, either showing it if it is
    available, or defaulting back to the original page.</para>

    <para>Translations for the Debian website are being created for 33
    world languages, although only 10 language temas have more than 500 pages translated
    out of over 3000 available pages, and only 5 teams have translated more
    than 50% of the site.  It is a very large and demanding task, but one we
    assign priority, so there is a great deal of translation activity around
    the Debian website. New languages will continue to be added, and further
    pages translated.</para>

    <para>The web server is based on content managed by the
    <command>wml</command> program ,which allows separation of templates
    and content, and also provides a mechanism to generate content
    within the pages on <emphasis>compile</emphasis>. Wml is to HTML
    what a C source is to its object code.</para>

    <para>Most of the information on the web server is available in a
    directory tree, handled through CVS (at cvs.debian.org). In that
    tree, there is a directory for every language in which the website is
    translated. In principle, all the languages follow the
    directory hierarchy defined in the original (English) pages although,
    depending on the actual content translated, the contents of each
    subdirectory within a language might vary. There is also a specific
    location for translation teams' content which is not translations, but
    rather specific content written in that language, usually specific to that
    language/culture. The mechanism for generating the pages is based on
    <command>Makefile</command> in such a way that all the wml files in a given
    directory are compiled and published together. The use of included files
    means translators do not need to concern themselves with the content of the
    Makefile files.</para>

    <para>Thanks to the independence of real content and aesthetic
    information, translators can simply take the original (English) wml
    files, move them to their own directories and translate them. The
    templates that generate the website itself need not be translated,
    unless specifically required. The templates use wml's internationalisation
    tools and <command>gettext</command> to extract and present the
    translatable information (including headers, footers, menus, buttons, both
    interactive and passive text) in all the pages for translation.</para>

    <para> One of the main issues in ongoing translation is the need to be able
    to monitor changes in the original content. In particular, translators need to know
    which changes require updating translations. The web server has the same
    problem. Using content negotiation to detect a user's language settings, is
    only looking to see if a translation exists and can be displayed, and is
    not aware of the status of any translated content. So it's possible that
    users might be presented with out-of-date information. This  issue would
    not exist if the translation were removed when it was no longer current,
    since the web server would then simply provide the default language
    (English) to the user. However, many changes to the website are not
    fundamental changes, or are typo fixes to the original document, so it
    would seem senseless to provide the original  document in these situations,
    since the translation (even if out of date) would still be useful to
    website readers who can't understand the original content.</para>

    <para>To deal with this currency issue proactively, the website development
    team implemented a mechanism to detect out-of-date translations, based on
    <emphasis>translation headers</emphasis>. These headers are included in
    translated documents, describing which original file they translated, and
    specifying the CVS revision used. The use of this header makes it possible
    to introduce several additional tools to facilitate effective translations:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

    <listitem><para>an automatic program that can be run in the
    directory tree to provide a translator with a list of the documents
    that have not been updated for a given language. This is done
    through comparison of the current CVS revision of the original
    file with the CVS revision that the translated document states it
    used as a base for the translation;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>a wml toolkit that, at the same time pages
    are compiled (once a day), checks if the wml file being handled is
    a translation or not, and if it is, if it is current. It uses this
    information to introduce a predefined text in the output document,
    that tells the reader if the translation is not up to date, and
    points to the original translation (the text varies based on how
    out-of-date the translation is). The same tools will also add a
    footer to all pages, to list the translations available not simply
    for the website in any degree, but for each specific page.</para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>More information is available <ulink
    url="http://www.debian.org/devel/website/translating">on the website
    development reference</ulink>.</para>

    <para>There are further tools, also based on this mechanism, that provide
    <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/devel/website/stats/">statistics
    related to the translation effort</ulink>, including <ulink
    url="http://people.debian.org/~peterk/outdated/">statistics on
    out-of-date translations</ulink><footnote><para>Translations that are 
    out-of-date for more than six months are automatically removed,
    regardless of the number of revisions they are behind. For more information
    read
    <ulink
    url="http://lists.debian.org/debian-www/2004/01/msg00323.html"/></para>
    </footnote>.</para>

    <para>Since translations have to follow the creation of the original
    content, they will typically lag slightly behind the translated content in
    an active website. This mechanism provides a way for translators to work on
    translations at their own pace, while ensuring users reading the content
    know how current it is, and have the option to switch to the original
    content.</para>


  </section>

  <section id="programs">
    <title>Translation of Debian tools</title>

  <para>Internationalisation of the Debian distribution also involves
  the internationalisation and translation of the tools developed
  within the distribution itself. This includes the translation of the
  installation system (<command>d-i</command>), of the package
  management system tools (<command>dpkg</command>,
  <command>dselect</command>, <command>apt</command>,
  <command>aptitude</command>), of desktop menu management
  (<command>menu</command>) and of other Debian tools such as
  <command>debconf</command>.</para>

  <para>Without proper internationalisation or translation of these
  tools,  the majority of current and potential users will not be able to use
  or manage the Debian GNU/Linux operating system effectively.</para>

  <para>The following sections describe the efforts in
  internationalisation and in the translation of different parts of the Debian
  GNU/Linux distribution within the Debian project itself</para>

  <section id="debconf">
    <title>Debconf translation</title>

  <para>Debconf translation covers the translation of all
  interactions with the system administrator while installing packages
  (or installing the entire system).</para>

<section id="po-debconf"><title>Maintainers' tasks - internationalisation</title>

<para>The <ulink
url="http://www.debian.org/doc/manuals/developers-reference/">Developer's
reference</ulink> recommends using the debconf protocol for user
interaction. This presents information in a standardised way,
easier for the user to follow and understand,
and also allows more effective localisation of user interaction.  Allowing debconf
templates to be translatable <ulink
url="http://www.debian.org/doc/manuals/developers-reference/ch-best-pkging-practices.en.html#s-bpp-i18n">is
also a recommended practice</ulink>.</para>

<para>This requirement could even become mandatory in the future. This was
mentioned for Etch but unfortunately no-one followed through, by proposing the
required changes to the policy for this to take place. Debconf, untranslated, is
a bottleneck between the users and your software. Translate it, and it's an
access conduit.</para>

<para>Debconf translations involve the <command>po-debconf</command>
package which has now become a standard in Debian. Even though not
mandated by the policy, all packages using <command>debconf</command> for user
interaction should use <command>po-debconf</command>.  It automates a number of
the repetitive but essential tasks, and ensures that translators receive update
notices for your templates. This is best practice in the field, ensuring a much
higher translation rate.</para>

<para>The details of <command>po-debconf</command> are well covered in
its man page (<command>po-debconf(7)</command>). In short,
strings (Description, Choices and Default fields) should
be prepended with the underscore character in the debconf templates
file. If you do so, they will be included automatically in the list of
translatable material.</para>

<para>The <command>debconf-updatepo</command> program gathers all the
translatable material in a Portable Object Template (POT) file located
under <filename>debian/po</filename> in the package build tree.  This
templates file is then used as a reference by translators to create a
Portable Object file for their languages, using the language
<ulink url="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/englangn.html">ISO 639</ulink>
code.</para>

<section><title>Consistency of style</title>

<para>Users will often see a series of several debconf screens in a row. A
consistent style in both writing and presentation considerably
improves the perception of professionalism in the overall Debian
distribution.</para>

<para>Unfortunately, the original English strings very often lack this
consistency, and despite <ulink
url="http://www.debian.org/doc/developers-reference/ch-best-pkging-practices.fr.html#s-bpp-config-mgmt">some
efforts in the Developer's Reference</ulink> to give maintainers
advice about writing style for debconf templates, the manner of addressing users often varies wildly:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>use of the first person;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>use or not of interrogative form for input-style templates;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>repeated interrogative form in long and short description of templates;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>varying enumeration styles;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>use of specific references to some of the debconf interface-specific
 widgets or behaviour (talking about "previous" or "next" screens,
 assuming that boolean templates use Yes/No style questions, etc.).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>In general, maintainers should follow translators' advice when they
suggest improvements to original templates.</para>

<para>
The French team, and more specifically Thomas Huriaux, has setup
<ulink
url="http://haydn.debian.org/~thuriaux-guest/templates/templates_by_packages.html">a
dedicated page</ulink> which automatically tracks down the most common
"errors" with regards to this recommendation.  </para>


</section>
<section><title>Repetitive strings</title>

<para>A great deal of user interaction in debconf templates involves similar
questions or input, such as web server configuration for packages that
provide web services, database interactions for RDBMS-related packages
or packages that use databases, basic identification, etc.</para>

<para>To avoid such repetition and the wasted time associated with it, packages
aimed at providing common methods, as well as common debconf
templates for such use have recently appeared in the Debian distribution.
The <command>dbconfig-common</command> package is one of them.</para>

<para>Maintainers are encouraged to use these packages, and to help improve
them for better quality and efficiency. The use of the debconf
<emphasis>register</emphasis> commands is also encouraged in some cases, when a package
needs to use strings or templates provided by another package.</para>

</section>
<section><title>Translation maintenance - localisation
assistants</title>

<para>The part of this paper which deals with i18n/l10n of Debian specific
programs(see <xref linkend="programs"/>) introduces the concept of
"localisation assistants".</para>

<para>As the maintenance of debconf translations is usually very simple,
this paper does not enforce the use of localisation assistants, except
in the case of packages with a high number of templates and/or
packages listed a top priority packages for translators (packages
which belong to the Debian Installer "levels" packages, or very popular
packages).</para>

<para>However, in any situation where the maintenance of debconf translations
becomes a hassle for them, package maintainers are encouraged to cooperate with
a localisation assistant. The <ulink
url="http://lists.debian.org/debian-i18n">debian-i18n mailing list</ulink> is
the entry point that should be used to "recruit"
localisation assistants.</para>

</section>

</section>

<section><title>Translation work - localisation</title>

<section><title>Getting translation material</title>

<para>Although everyone can access debconf translation material by downloading
each package source and looking in <filename>debian/po</filename>,
translators are encouraged to use <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/intl/l10n/po-debconf/">links from the translation
statistics pages</ulink>.</para>

</section>
<section><title>Priorities</title>


<para>Although debconf templates are fairly small, there are over 695 individual
debconf templates, a fairly large and repetitive task for translators. 
The number of Debian packages with translatable material for debconf
is pretty important. As of this writing these 695 packages with
translatable debconf material add up to about 10000 strings to translate.</para>

<para>Recent changes to the translation statistics pages now allow sorting
packages by their popularity, using data from the <command>popularity-contest</command>
package. This was achieved to avoid translators spending their effective time on rarely-used packages, and to ensure commonly-used packages get translated first.</para>

</section>
<section><title>Statistics</title>

<para>Statistics for debconf translations are gathered on the <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/intl/l10n/po-debconf/rank">Debian l10n
status pages</ulink> and are separated from the translation
statistics for individual programs. These pages also give access to the
translation material collected by the statistics robot operated by the Debian
i18n team.</para>

</section>
<section><title>Translation</title>

<para>Translation usually involves copying the
<filename>templates.pot</filename> file to <filename>&lt;code&gt;.po</filename>
(where <emphasis>code</emphasis> is the language code it is being translated
to), filling in this file's header with appropriate information, then using a
Portable object editing tool (or any text editor) to enter the translations for
all the strings.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Checking translations</title>

<para>Translators can test the debconf PO files by using the
<command>podebconf-display-po</command> tool from the
<command>po-debconf</command> package. They will need to install
this package on their system.</para>

<para>A locale for the tested language must be built on the system (which
can be achieved by "dpkg-reconfigure locales") and the LC_MESSAGES
variable should be set to this locale.</para>

<para>It is recommended to test the debconf templates by using the debconf
dialog interface in a 80x25 screen.</para>

<para><command>podebconf-display-po</command> has a few quirks,
especially when some strings are shared among several templates, so it
should not be relied on blindly. Despite this, it has already proven 
extremely helpful in detecting formatting issues.</para>

</section>

<section><title>Style consistency</title>

<para>Translations need a consistent writing style, just as the original
strings do, to communicate effectively.  This information, and the way it is
presented, also functions as the public face of that application or document,
and of the overall project.</para>

<para>While it is true that, as yet, the original English strings in many
packages may lack this professional consistency, translators can greatly help
package maintainers a great deal in improving accuracy and style.  They can
report syntax and style errors as bug reports against the relevant packages.
Ultimately, this partnership between package maintainers and translators not
only produces an application accessible by many more people, but also a higher
overall quality of presentation.</para>

<para>Translators should aim for consistency in their own translation
work. Even if the original strings do not follow writing-style recommendations,
translators should adapt their translation to be consistent in their language,
to create a high-quality translation as an achievement in its own right.</para>

<para>Translation teams, and the QA work they do, have indeed a great role to
play in this overall improvement of presentation consistency.  They are capable
not only of processing information for translation, but also of reviewing it as
information. Through this additional review process, the quality of information
presentation in debconf templates should continue to improve.  </para>

</section>

<section><title>Sending new translations and translation updates to maintainers</title>

<para>Translators should send debconf translation updates to maintainers via
the <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/">Bug Tracking System</ulink>, even when the
update is requested by a maintainer using an automated tool to call for
updates. Such bug reports should use the
"l10n" and "patch" tags, and severity "wishlist"</para>

<para>They should be filed against the <emphasis>source</emphasis> package
rather than against a binary package.</para>

<para>The use of the reportbug utility is recommended.</para>

<para>A standardised bug title is recommended: "&lt;package&gt;:
[intl:&lt;code&gt;] &lt;Language&gt; debconf templates translation", where
&lt;package&gt; is the source package name, &lt;code&gt; the language ISO code and
&lt;Language&gt; is the language name in English.
</para>

<para>
Here's an example of reporting the French translation of the
<command>geneweb</command> package. Of course, in the example below,
<command>geneweb</command> should be replaced by the appropriate
package name:</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
bubulle@mykerinos:~/tmp> reportbug geneweb
*** Welcome to reportbug.  Use ? for help at prompts. ***
Using 'Christian Perrier &lt;bubulle@debian.org&gt;' as your from address.
Detected character set: UTF-8
Please change your locale if this is incorrect.

Getting status for geneweb...
Checking for newer versions at packages.debian.org...
Will send report to Debian (per lsb_release).
Querying Debian BTS for reports on geneweb (source)...
14 bug reports found:

(snip all bug reports for geneweb)

(1-14/14) Is the bug you found listed above [y|N|m|r|q|s|f|?]? n
Maintainer for geneweb is 'Christian Perrier &lt;bubulle@debian.org&gt;'.
Looking up dependencies of geneweb...
*** The following debconf settings were detected:
  geneweb/run_mode: Always on
  geneweb/remainingdir:
* geneweb/remove_databases: false
  geneweb/port: 2317
* geneweb/lang: French
Include these settings in your report [Y|n|q|?]? n

Please briefly describe your problem (you can elaborate in a moment; an empty response will stop reportbug). This
should be a concise summary of what is wrong with the package, for example, "fails to send email" or "does not
start with -q option specified."
> [INTL:fr] French debconf templates translation
Rewriting subject to 'geneweb: [INTL:fr] French debconf templates translation'

Enter any additional addresses this report should be sent to; press ENTER after each address. Press ENTER on a
blank line to continue.
>

How would you rate the severity of this problem or report?

1 critical        makes unrelated software on the system (or the whole system) break, or causes serious data
                  loss, or introduces a security hole on systems where you install the package.
2 grave           makes the package in question unusable by most or all users, or causes data loss, or introduces
                  a security hole allowing access to the accounts of users who use the package.
3 serious         is a severe violation of Debian policy (that is, the problem is a violation of a 'must' or
                  'required' directive); may or may not affect the usability of the package. Note that non-severe
                  policy violations may be 'normal,' 'minor,' or 'wishlist' bugs. (Package maintainers may also
                  designate other bugs as 'serious' and thus release-critical; however, end users should not do
                  so.)
4 important       a bug which has a major effect on the usability of a package, without rendering it completely
                  unusable to everyone.
5 does-not-build  a bug that stops the package from being built from source. (This is a 'virtual severity'.)
6 normal          a bug that does not undermine the usability of the whole package; for example, a problem with a
                  particular option or menu item.
7 minor           things like spelling mistakes and other minor cosmetic errors that do not affect the core
                  functionality of the package.
8 wishlist        suggestions and requests for new features.

Please select a severity level: [normal] 8
Do any of the following apply to this report?

1 l10n          This bug reports a localization/internationalization issue.

2 patch         You are including a patch to fix this problem.

3 experimental  This bug only applies to a package in the experimental branch of Debian.

4 none

Please select tags: (one at a time) [none] 1
- selected: l10n
Please select tags: (one at a time) [done] 2
- selected: l10n patch
Please select tags: (one at a time) [done]

(snip editor being spawned)


Report will be sent to "Debian Bug Tracking System" &lt;submit@bugs.debian.org&gt;
Submit this report on geneweb (e to edit) [Y|n|a|c|e|i|l|m|p|q|?]? a
Choose a file to attach: /home/bubulle/tmp/fr.po
Report will be sent to "Debian Bug Tracking System" &lt;submit@bugs.debian.org&gt;
Attachments:
 /home/bubulle/tmp/fr.po
Submit this report on geneweb (e to edit) [Y|n|a|c|e|i|l|m|p|q|?]? y   
</screen>
</informalexample>

</section>

</section>

</section>

<!-- Clytie work merged up to here -->

  <section id="ddtp">
    <title>DDTP</title>

      <para>Another translation project is the translation of the
      descriptions of the software packages offerred for Debian.
      This project is named the <emphasis>Debian
      Description Translation Project</emphasis> (DDTP).</para>

      <para>Each package shipped in Debian is provided with
      two descriptions: a short description (less than 80 characters)
      and a long one (of variable length). The first one describes
      briefly what the package does and the second one describes its
      main functionalities, characteristics, differences with other
      software, etc. This information is vital for users who are
      looking for a given functionality within the (huge) quantity of
      software provided in the Debian distribution. The package
      management tools include interfaces to do word (or regular
      expression) searches through these descriptions.</para>

      <para>However, the fact that all these descriptions are only
      available in the English language makes it difficult for users
      that have already installed the system to look for new software
      they might want. Users not fluent in English might not be
      capable to define their needs in a foreign language to look for
      the specific software they are looking for.</para>

      <para>The description translation project started in order to
      solve this problem for end users. This project was started
      initially by two different work groups in the year 2002,
      resulting in two different management systems (one based on
      e-mail and another based on a web
      application<footnote><para>This web application was developed by
      members of the Spanish translation team and available at <ulink
      url="http://www.laespiral.org/"/></para></footnote>. The
      framework was based on Perl scripts that collected descriptions
      and provided an e-mail interface for translators (translators
      could request new translation through email and submit them
      using the same interface). All translations are stored in a
      simple file with a database holding the status of the
      translation (new, needs to be reviewed, out of date, etc.). Most
      notably, the framework did not use PO files for translations
      which got it many objections from some translation teams.</para>

      <para>The translations from the web based interface one of these
      systems have later been merged on with the other one. The project
      was used by different translation teams. When Debian systems
      were <ulink
      url="http://www.debian.org/News/2003/20031121">compromised</ulink>
      in November 2003 the main framework was disconnected pending a
      review of the source code.</para>

      <para>The Brazilian team (Otavio Salvador) later developed
      patches for <command>apt</command> to support the use of the translated
      descriptions in it. This patch (<ulink
      url="http://people.ubuntu.com/~mvo/arch/ubuntu/apt--ddtp--0/">apt-ddtp</ulink>)
      was ported to the 0.6 code base, with the help of some other
      developers, including Michael Vogt. Later, in April 2005, an
      <ulink url="http://alioth.debian.org/projects/ddtp/">Alioth
      project</ulink> was started and the original source code of the
      translation framework was moved to a <ulink
      url="http://svn.debian.org/wsvn/ddtp/">SVN
      repository</ulink>.</para>

      <para>As of this writing the DDTP project does not have an
      interface to submit translations. The translations already done
      for descriptions can be downloaded from <ulink
      url="http://ddtp.debian.org/"/>, but they are not being
      updated.</para>

      <para>This work, however, has been reused in Ubuntu. Currently,
      the Ubuntu package descriptions are imported into Ubuntu's
      translation framework: <ulink
      url="http://launchpad.ubuntu.com/rosetta">Rosetta</ulink> using
      the po/pot extraction/assemble tools developed by Michael Vogt,
      and available at <ulink
      url="http://people.ubuntu.com/~mvo/arch/ubuntu/apt-ddtp-tools--main--0/">michael.vogt@ubuntu.com--2005/apt-ddtp-tools--main--0</ulink>.
      The tools converted the Packages file to a pot file that is then
      imported into Rosetta. Rosetta then generates the PO files from the
      translations that can be downloaded and converted into a
      Translations-$lang file that apt-ddtp understands.</para>

  </section>

  </section>

  <section id="translation_installation">
    <title>Translation of installed systems</title>

    <para>A common need for users installing a Debian system is to end
    up with a fully localised system that does not need to be set up
    in order to be useful for users who require a given locale for
    being supported. Besides having a fully I18n Debian Installer
    there are several things that help set up an internationalised
    Debian system.</para>

  <section id="localization_config">
    <title>Localization-config</title>

  <para><command>Localization-config</command> is a tool to setup the
  configuration of programs in order to use a default language for the
  system as defined by the system administrator. This tool was
  initially written by Konstantinos Margaritis, developed for
  Skolelinux and was later integrated with Debian and uploaded in August
  2004. It was later integrated in the Debian installer for sarge
  (through <command>base-config</command>).</para>
  
  <para>This tool tries to ease the way that administrators (or, even,
  the Debian Installer) set up a fully localised system. In a system,
  localisation begins by defining the preferred locale but there are
  many tools that need to be specifically configured to use a given
  locale. This tool can run after and before package installation to
  adjust its configuration to use a given language through the use of
  a collection of scripts. Each of the available scripts adjust the
  configuration of a single package for a number of languages. Please note
  that this tool is targeted for system configuration. Users wishing
  to change their own locale (but not the system's) should use
  <command>set-language-env</command> (in the
  <command>language-env</command> package).</para>

  <para>In order to use this tool, the system administrator have to call one
  script, <command>update-locale-config</command>, providing the
  desired locale as a parameter. This script calls all other scripts
  in <filename>/usr/lib/localization-config</filename>.  If the -p flag is
  used, the *.preinst scripts are called, else (default) the
  *.postinst scripts are called.  The preinst scripts are supposed to
  be run when you need to do configuration of a package before it is
  installed (main use is by preseeding debconf values of the
  package). The postinst scripts are there when a package does not
  support this kind of preconfiguration (such KDE, gdm, etc.) and has
  to be configured by modifying its configuration file.</para>

  <para>In order to prevent modifying new configuration file formats
  the scripts first checks the version of the package it should
  configure, in three different ways:</para>

  <itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>check the version of the installed package.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>check the version of the package available available
  in the configured repository (that is, what is the version of the
  package you would install if you use
  <command>apt</command>).</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>if both of the checks above fail, try getting the version
  from <filename>/etc/debian_version</filename>. This method should never be
  called if everything works as expected.</para></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The version of the package is used to define version maps,
  since some versions might need to be configured in slightly
  different ways. The wrapper scripts will call the appropriate script
  under the proper folder (woody, sarge, etc) and do the actual
  configuration.</para>

  <para>Localization-config currently configures:</para>

  <itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>Dictionaries-common (<command>ispell</command>): preseeds the preferred dictionary;</para></listitem>
  

  <listitem><para>fontconfig: implement fonts substitution (currently only for Greek);</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Gdm: sets the default language for sessions;</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>KDE: modifies the language settings of <filename>/etc/kde3/system.kdeglobals</filename> and <filename>/etc/kde3/kdm/kdmrc</filename>. It can also modify the settings of the <command>ktouch</command> program by adjusting <filename>/etc/kde3/ktouchrc</filename>;</para></listitem>
  
  <listitem><para>Links: Sets the preferred language for browsing by
  modifying <filename>/etc/links.cfg</filename>;</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Ltsp: Sets the X keyboard map by modifying <filename>/opt/ltsp/i386/etc/lts.conf</filename>;</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Lynx:  Sets the preferred language for browsing by
  modifying <filename>/etc/lynx.cfg</filename>;</para></listitem>
  
  <listitem><para>Mozilla: Sets the preferred language for browsing by
  setting the UserAgent locale and accepted languages at <filename>/etc/mozilla/prefs.js</filename>;</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Xfree86 and Xorg: preseeds the character set for the
  language.</para></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Localization-config is still work in progress and members of
  the different i18n teams still need to review the available scripts
  in order to integrate their own languages in the installation
  process. Moreover, due to the changes introduced in the Debian
  Installer early in 2006 (in which base-config was removed and
  introduced into the first stage of the installed), this package
  needs to be re-integrated into the <emphasis>etch</emphasis>
  installer.</para>

  <para>New i18n scripts need to be written also for programs such as:
  <command>locale-purge</command> (<filename>/etc/locale.nopurge</filename>, TeX/LaTeX
  (including hyphenation rules defined at
  <filename>/etc/texmf/language.dat</filename>), console settings (including
  <filename>/etc/inputrc</filename> and the console keymap by preseeding <command>console-common</command>), Mutt (locale and
  charset at <filename>/etc/Muttrc</filename>), Mozilla's Firebird (same
  values as those configured already for Mozilla), etc.</para>


  </section> <!-- localization config -->

  <section id="language_tasks">
    <title>Language tasks</title>

    <para>The Debian task selection tool, called
    <command>tasksel</command> is run in every new system installation
    and allows to define a set of packages aimed for specific purposes.</para>

    <para>One widely developed used of tasksel are "language
    tasks". These are tasks that are installed depending on the
    installation language. They should feature sets of packages that
    are specific to the related language.</para>

    <section><title>Sets of language tasks</title>

    <para>There are currently two language tasks per language: one
    &lt;language&gt; task which depends on nothing but standard
    packages, and one &lt;language&gt;-desktop task which depends on
    the standard desktop task.</para>

    <para>Packages in language tasks can include localisation packages
    for software that are installed by other tasks or by the standard
    system. For instance, the &lt;language&gt;-desktop tasks install
    localisation packages for the packages that are part of the
    standard desktop task (kde-i18n-*, openoffice.org-l10n-*, etc.).</para>

    <para>These tasks can also include packages that are needed for
    the rendering of the given language: TTF or Postscript fonts for
    &lt;language&gt;-desktop tasks, console fonts for &lt;language&gt;
    tasks, etc.</para>


    </section> <!-- sets of language tasks -->

    <section><title>Maintenance of language tasks</title>

    <para>Adding new language tasks should be partly automated by the
    tasksel maintenance team, i.e. the Debian Installer team. As soon as
    a new languages appears in the D-I supported languages, an
    equivalent language task should be added, if at least one specific
    package motivates it (for instance a localisation package for on
    of the packages that are part of the desktop tasks.</para>

    <para>Translation teams and translators should also be active by
    proposing enhancement to tasks related to their language.</para>

    <para>New tasks should be reported as wishlist bug reports again
    the tasksel package.</para>

  </section> <!-- maintenance of language tasks -->

  </section> <!-- language tasks -->


<!-- jfs : -XX packages -->
  <section id="packages">
    <title>Translation packages</title>

<!-- FIXME: TBD -->
  <para>This section will be completed in further releases of this paper</para>

  </section>


</section> <!-- End of the Debian installation -->

<!-- jfs: DDP+installer+manpages -->
  <section id="doc-l10n">
    <title>Translation of documentation</title>

  <para>Users of an operating system require, in order to be able to
  use it, both online and offline documentation.</para>

  <para>In UNIX systems, online documentation is typically handled
  through manual pages (retrieved through the use of
  <command>man</command>)<footnote><para>The GNU project prefers the use of
  <command>info</command> documentation but most upstream developers
  just provide manpages.</para></footnote>. In Desktop environments both KDE
  and GNOME provide online help systems.</para>

  <para>Offline documentation includes documents such as the Debian
  Installation Manual, the Debian Reference Guide, or the Security
  Debian Manual. These manuals, developed by the <ulink
  url="http://www.debian.org/doc/ddp">Debian Documentation
  Project</ulink> (DDP), are typically printed by users and, sometimes,
  read from other (non-Debian) systems at the project's website. Some of the
  manuals are included in the official CD set and most of them are 
  also available through Debian packages.</para>

  <para>Obviously, users not proficient with English will prefer
  documentation in a language they're familiar with. This is why translation of
  documentation is needed.</para>

  <section>
  <title>SGML/XML documentation</title>

  <para>The <emphasis>DDP</emphasis> project develops documentation
  for Debian written, primarily, in SGML format. The first
  documentation produced by the project was written in a variant of
  SGML called <emphasis>debiandoc-sgml</emphasis> for which tools were
  developed to convert the SGML documents into different formats (HTML
  for online viewing, PDF and PostSCript for printing, and simple
  text). The latest documentation written by members of the project or
  revisions of available documentation (such as the Debian
  Installation Manual) has been written using XML and more specifically
  Docbook-XML which is widely used by many free software
  projects<footnote><para>Including distributions such as Red Hat
  GNU/Linux, or the <ulink url="http://www.tldp.org">Linux
  Documentation Project</ulink></para></footnote>.</para>

  <para>The translation of documentation written in SGML or XML format,
  however, faces some initial issues:</para>

  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem><para>SGML documents are usually written in a single
    (big) file. Since translation teams are typically created in order
    to handle (small) documents this means that the translation
    coordinator has to break up the original file in chunks;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Translators cannot directly use the tools they are
    used to such as tools intended to work on PO files;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Automatic publication of documentation in HTML format of
    documentation needs to be adapted so that they are capable of
    publishing both the original document and the translations without
    one conflicting with each other;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Automatic publication of documentation in PS/PDF
    needs to be able to handle non-European character sets
    (i.e. specific fonts) properly;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Tracking of changes and updates in SGML/XML
    documents needs to be done through source diffs (which requires
    access to a revision control system). If a single file is being
    used, tracking differences will be more difficult;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Diffing tools handle poorly the fact that text can
    be wrapped to different column lengths and paragraphs might be
    "moved" around without actually changing
    context.</para></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In order to overcome these issues, the document writers,
  in cooperation with translators, have introduced significant changes to
  how documentation is written:</para>


  <itemizedlist>

    <listitem><para>SGML documents are broken up into smaller files
    (typically one file per chapter);</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>New tools have been introduced to be able to
    convert SGML/XML documents into PO files:
    <command>po-debiandoc</command> (now deprecated),
    <command>po4a</command> (see <xref linkend="po4a-for-doc"/>) and
    <command>poxml</command>;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>New tools have been introduced to be able to
    detect when files within a document have changed:
    <command>doc-check</command> (see <xref linkend="doc-check"/>) and track the specific changes
    through the revision control system;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>The publishing toolset (based around
    <filename>Makefiles</filename>) has been adapted in order to build
    and publish both the original file and the available translations.</para></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Currently, the Debian Documentation Project uses the CVS
  server at cvs.debian.org<footnote><para>The web interface can be
  accessed at <ulink
  url="http://cvs.debian.org/ddp/manuals.sgml/?root=debian-doc"/>.</para></footnote>.
  Documentation is compiled through a set of Makefiles and published
  on <ulink url="http://www.debian.org">the official project web site</ulink>, which updates its copy of the CVS repository and
  compiles all the documentation daily. The CVS server at
  cvs.debian.org holds most (but not all) of the documentation
  available. The most notable exception is the <emphasis>Debian
  Installer Manual</emphasis> which is available in the <ulink
  url="svn://svn.d-i.alioth.debian.org/svn/d-i/trunk/manual">SVN
  repository of the Debian Installer project on Alioth</ulink> (<ulink
  url="http://svn.debian.org/wsvn/d-i/trunk/manual/?rev=0&amp;sc=0">web
  access to the SVN repository</ulink>). The development version of
  the Debian Installation Guide is available at <ulink
  url="http://d-i.alioth.debian.org/manual/">the Debian Installer project's web
  pages</ulink> also on Alioth.</para>

  <para>Translators either get access to the CVS or use the original
  documentation maintainer as a proxy to publish the information in
  the CVS. When a translation is added to an available document the
  maintainer typically needs to update the <emphasis>LANGS</emphasis> (or
  <emphasis>LANGUAGES</emphasis>) variable in the document's
  <filename>Makefile</filename> in order to tell the publication
  system to also build copies for that language. If the added
  translation builds, it should be available in the Debian website
  after the next daily build.</para>

  <para>In order to track the changes of documentation and when a
  translation needs to be updated, document maintainers and
  translators use the <command>doc-check</command> tool. See <xref
  linkend="doc-check"/>.</para>

  </section><!-- SGML documentation -->

  <section id="manpages-l10n">
  <title>Debian manpages translation</title>

  <para>There are mainly two types of manpages provided within the
  Debian operating system: those packaged with upstream software (such
  as binutils or gcc) and those written for Debian tools provided in
  Debian-only packages. The translation of manpages of upstream
  software are typically provided either within the package itself or
  within <filename>manpages-XX</filename> package
  (where <filename>XX</filename> is a given language codename)
  the case of the translation of the <ulink
  url="http://www.kernel.org/pub/linux/docs/manpages/">Linux
  manpages</ulink>.</para>

  <section>
  <title>Manpages packages</title>

  <para>At the time of this writing the following translation
  manpages packages are available: </para>

  <itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>manpages-de and manpages-de-dev - German manpages
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>manpages-es and manpages-es-extra - Spanish man pages
  </para></listitem>
  
  <listitem><para>manpages-fi - Finnish man pages </para></listitem>
  
  <listitem><para>manpages-fr - French version of the manual pages
  </para></listitem>
  
  <listitem><para>manpages-hu - Hungarian manpages </para></listitem>
  
  <listitem><para>manpages-it - Italian man pages</para></listitem>
  
  <listitem><para>manpages-ja and manpages-ja-dev - Japanese version
  of the manual pages</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>manpages-ko - Korean version of the manual pages
</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>manpages-nl - Dutch manpages</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>manpages-pl - Polish man pages </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>manpages-pt and manpages-pt-dev - Portuguese
Versions of the Manual Pages</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>manpages-ru - Russian translations of Linux
manpages</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>manpages-tr - Turkish version of the manual pages</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>manpages-zh - Chinese manual pages</para></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Those manpage packages contain, for the most part, the same
  manpages available in the <filename>manpages</filename> or
  <filename>manpages-dev</filename> packages although some packages
  contain extra manpages.</para>

  <para>Users will see the translated manpages through the
  internationalisation mechanisms of the <command>man</command> command
  which will review, when asked to present a manpage, if a translation
  is available under <filename>/usr/share/man/XX</filename> (with
  XX being the language code of the user's
  environment<footnote><para>As defined through the LANG
  variable</para></footnote>). Consequently, the Debian installation
  system will install both <filename>manpages</filename> and
  <filename>manpages-XX</filename> through a default installation if
  the user selects an specific language task for which manpages are
  available.</para>

  </section><!-- Manpages packages -->

  <section><title>Issues with manpage translations</title>

  <para>One of the main issues with manpages, however, is that there
  is no provisions in the <command>man</command> to detect when a
  translation is out of date. As a consequence, users reading
  translated manual pages might be reading out of date content that
  does not really apply to the latest version of the program's man
  page.</para>

  <para>The translation project is also lacking a central web page
  where teams can see (at a glance) which manpages are available for
  translation, which translations are out of date, translated or
  untranslated and who is the last translator of the manpage.</para>

  <!-- TODO:
    There are also other I18N issues for some languages:
    * lexgrog only support some languages.
    * Whatis and apropos are badly internationalise.
    * man-db does not build indexes of the translated manpages
    * man does not support some encodings (I don't remember if this is the
      input or output encoding). This affect the Vietnameses pages. Some work
      has been done regarding this subject with groff-utf8.

    http://manpages.debian.net can be used to find manpages of a
    Debian system, but it does not reference translated man pages.

    Man pages translations are often done by team, which are not based on one
    distribution. This tends to distribute translations that does not
    correspond to the version/software distributed in debian.  (e.g. su is
    provided by shadow, and some of the su.1 translations describe coreutils'
    su).

  -->

  </section><!-- Issues with manpages translations -->

  <section><title>Translation of Debian manpages</title>

  <para>The translation of manpages specific to programs developed
  within the Debian project (such as the <command>dpkg</command> or
  <command>apt</command> tools) is a work that falls within the scope
  of the Debian translation teams.</para>

  <para>The translation of manpages for Debian programs are included
  within the Debian package itself, which means that translators have
  to request the Debian maintainer to include the translation in it,
  once finished. Since Debian programs are typically managed through
  common revision control repositories available to Debian developers
  or contributors (either at cvs.debian.org or at alioth.debian.org)
  active translators of a Debian program will typically have access to
  those resources and will be able to commit directly into the source
  control zone were manpages are included. It is worthwhile noting,
  that it is also common for people active in the program translation
  to work on the translation of the manpage so that the translation of
  the program messages and options is consistent with the manual page
  itself.</para>


  <para>In order to coordinate the translation of manpages and make it
  possible to track when the translation changes, the translation
  teams introduced the <filename>manpages</filename> in the CVS DDP
  area. This module includes several scripts in order to track
  manpages translations: <command>check_trans.pl</command> and
  <command>compare_files.pl</command><footnote><para>There is an
  additional script, <command>gen_db.pl</command>, used to generate
  the wml files used for the translation coordination database in the
  web page area</para></footnote>.</para>

  <para>This module was introduce since translators did not have
  access to the CVS repository of the programs for which the
  translations were going to be made available. Consequently, the
  original manpages themselves could not be modified to include a
  translation control header to keep track whenever one was modified.
  In order to keep track of translation status the CVS module holds
  <filename>INFO</filename> with meta-data of translated documents
  including:</para>

  <variablelist>
 
  <varlistentry><term>Manpage</term> <listitem><para>document's name in the CVS
  repository, may be different from the one in the source
  package. This is used as the document ID.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Encoding</term><listitem><para>Document's
  encoding.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Location</term><listitem><para>Location of this document
  in the source package (this value is only set when the source
  package does contain this document).</para></listitem> </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Original</term><listitem> <para>Original ID in the
  <filename>english/</filename> directory.</para></listitem> </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Original-CVS-Revision</term><listitem><para>CVS revision
  number of the original document on which a translation is
  based.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Translator</term><listitem><para>Translator's name, is be
  used to send automatic notifications when a translated man page is
  outdated.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

  <para>Original manpages are included in the
  <filename>english/</filename> directory of that CVS module by the
  translation teams and need to be updated manually when the original
  file is updated. Based on the meta-data information and the CVS
  revisions available for manpages the scripts can track when a
  manpage is outdated and notify the translator in charge of
  it.</para>

  <para>Unfortunately, this mechanism, initially developed by the
  French translation team and used by other teams, is not being
  maintained. There have been no updates in the English manpages for
  two years and translations have not been updated there
  either.</para>

  <!-- This is probably due to the switch to po4a? -->
  <!-- TODO: Talk about Locale::Po4a::Man? -->
  
  <para>FIXME: Describe use of po4a. The CVS-DDP module is not that much
  used anymore since most translators are now in the packages
  themselves...</para>

  </section><!-- Translation of Debian manpages -->

  </section><!-- Manpages translation -->
  
  <section><title>Coordination of documentation translation</title>

  <para>Initially, some of the translation projects (French and
  Spanish) introduced their own documentation translation management
  system<footnote><para>The Spanish management system (the status
  database has not been updated since January 2003) is available at
  <ulink
  url="http://www.debian.org/international/spanish/ltcp/"/>.</para></footnote>
  in order to coordinate the translation of the Debian Documentation
  Project published manuals. This management system was based on a
  flat database that included the available documents in the DDTP
  system and the status of translations. With the use of Perl scripts,
  this database was converted into HTML files that were published on
  the website so that the translation team could see which documents
  were being worked on and who was coordinating the
  translation.</para>

  <para>This system was not integrated with the document database
  provided by the DDP itself and the translation teams have, for a few
  years, made use of the translation robots (see <xref
  linkend="translation_robots"/>) in order too coordinate translation
  of documents themselves.</para>

  </section><!-- translation doc coordination -->


  </section> <!-- of the documentation section -->

  </chapter>


  <chapter id="infrastructure">
    <title>i18n/l10n infrastructure in Debian</title>
  

  <section id="po-statistics">
    <title>Po Translation statistics</title>

    <para>The Debian web site features statistics web pages under
    <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/intl/l10n" />. These pages
    collect statistical data about po-debconf and programs
    translations.</para>

    <para>The statistics are collected daily by a script run under a
    developer's account on people.debian.org (Denis Barbier account at
    the time of this writing). These statistics use material gathered
    by another script run under a developer's account on
    people.debian.org (Pierre Machard at the time of this
    writing).</para>

    <para>The statistics pages help translators learn about areas that
    need work such as updates for existing translations or new
    packages/material needing translation work.</para>

    <para>The pages also help translators to grab POT files and start
    working on new translations as well as PO files and work to
    complete them.</para>

    <para>Even though this system has proven to be highly useful during
    last years, it still carries a few weaknesses that prevent calling
    it an overall i18n/l10n infrastructure:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

    <listitem><para>it depends on scripts running under
    individual developers accounts;</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>it only gives statistics for the
    <emphasis>unstable</emphasis> branch of the distribution and thus does
    not allow to get statistics about l10n in testing during release
    preparation; </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>it does not track down the status of the work by
    translation teams and does no point the reader to the existing
    translation teams. For that reason, teams have developed their own
    tracking work method (some parts will be detailed in <xref linkend="translation_robots"/>)
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>it is not linked to the bug tracking system and
    does not allow checking whether an incomplete or missing
    translation has a pending fix in the BTS (and for how long the fix
    is pending) or in the package development revision control system.
    </para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A way to go would be integrating all these needs in a more
    general i18n/l10n infrastructure.</para>

    </section>
  <section id="web-statistics">
    <title>Website translation statistics</title>

    <para>Statistics for the translation of the Debian web site are
    collected in a different set of pages, run by different
    scripts.</para>

<!-- FIXME: TBD -->
    <para>This section will be completed in further releases of this paper</para>

    </section>
  <section id="d-i-statistics">
    <title>Debian installer translation statistics</title>
    
    <para>In order to track down issues more closely, the Debian
    Installer (D-I) i18n coordinators have setup translation statistics pages
    which gather the status of l10n for all core D-I packages as well
    as packages defined as part of the <ulink
    url="http://d-i.alioth.debian.org/doc/i18n/">D-I "levels" of
    translation</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>These pages point to the individual packages RCS
    directories and archives. They give translators a more accurate
    view of work to do and immediately reflect applied changes.</para>

    <para>They could be enhanced in a few ways:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

    <listitem><para>integrate them in the main web site. The status
    pages are generated by scripts running under Dennis Stampfer
    account. These scripts are not publicly visible and setting a new
    location for the pages would require Dennis expertise;
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>revamp the pages to make the main page less
    verbose. There is currently a big amount of information on this
    page and it should be redesigned as a whole web site, or
    integrated into a more general i18n infrastructure;
    </para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>allow getting statistics about all components in
    their own RCS trees, in unstable and in testing. This would allow
    getting a better picture of the real l10n status for releases of
    D-I.</para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A way to go could actually be integrating these requirements
    in a more general i18n/l10n infrastructure.</para>

  </section>

<!-- jfs -->
  <section id="translation_robots">
    <title>Translation robots</title>

  <para>One of the things that typically takes more time when
  coordinating translation projects is keeping track of what is each
  member of the team working on, and what is the precise status of each of the
  translations.</para>

  <para>The most well known translation robot is the one used by the
  <ulink url="http://translationproject.org/">Translation
  Project</ulink>. This is an e-mail service that takes care of PO
  file submissions for translations registered within the project. It
  checks if files sent to it are receivable, that is, if a translator
  has filled the translation disclaimer <footnote><para>Translators of
  the Translation Project have to send, through postal e-mail, a form
  that disclaims in writing by the translators, before being accepted
  for inclusion in the distribution. For more information, read <ulink
  url="http://translationproject.org/html/whydisclaim.html"/></para></footnote>. This
  robot also calls <command>msgfmt</command> to see if the PO file is
  healthy.  The robot also sends notices of updated PO files to the
  translation teams whenever translations need to be updated.</para>

  <para>This translation robot however, only tracks PO files, and only
  PO files of those GNU projects registered with it. Bearing in mind
  that the requirements of the translations teams in Debian were
  different, the translation teams started writing translation robots
  to handle their own translation process. This work was started by
  members of the French team and then reused by other translation
  teams including Spanish, Dutch, Brazilian Portuguese, and German.</para>

  <para>The translation coordination robot is an e-mail robot that
  "listens" to the mails sent to the translation teams mailing lists
  (debian-l10n-XXXX) and looks for a set of pseudo-urls in the
  messages' subjects. These pseudo-urls are composed of a translation
  status and a translation item (see <xref linkend="pseudo_urls"/>). The
  robot takes this information to compose a list of items being
  translated, the status of the translation and the translator in
  charge of it.</para>

  <para>This is a useful tool for both translation coordinators and
  members of the translation teams. Any member can, at a glance, see
  the status of a translation and help if help is needed (for
  translations or reviews). It also helps people detect translations
  that are stalled (a translator stated that they were going to work
  on it, but didn't finish actually finish it).</para>


  <para>Currently, there are several translation robots in
  place. First, there is a <ulink
  url="http://people.debian.org/~bertol/">generic robot</ulink> that
  handles different mailing lists by crawling the web site information
  with a set of <ulink
  url="http://people.debian.org/~bertol/scripts/dl10n/">scripts</ulink>.
  This robot is used by most translation teams, although some teams
  use their own robot, currently active are the: Spanish team which
  uses its own robot, available at <ulink
  url="http://www.debian.org.es/cgi-bin/l10n.cgi?team=es">Spanish
  translation coordination robot</ulink>, <ulink
  url="http://dutch.debian.net/">Dutch translation coordination
  robot</ulink>, <ulink url="http://ca.debian.net/">Catalonian
  translation coordination robot</ulink>. These last robots, instead
  of crawling the web site, use real e-mail addresses which are
  subscribed to the team's mailing lists and handle messages in real
  time through procmail filters that filter this information to the
  translation robot's status database.</para>

  <section id="translation_stages"><title>Translation stages</title>

  <para>Translations evolve through the following stages:</para>

  <itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>First, a translation needs to be done when there is
  a new (untranslated) item or document. Typically, the translation team coordinator asks somebody in the team to work on it;</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Then, a member of the translation team answers by
  saying that (s)he will work on that item;</para></listitem>


  <listitem><para>Once the translator finishes the translation (s)he
  sends the item for review to the translation mailing
  list; </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>After several reviews by peers, the translation
  is finally changed and a new version is sent for a final review;
  </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>The translator then picks the final version and
  submits it to the upstream maintainer. This is sometimes a package
  maintainer, but it can also be somebody with access to the CVS where
  the translations are maintained. Typically, for some translations,
  this step involves translators using the Debian Bug Tracking System
  to contact the maintainers (see <xref
  linkend="l10n_bts"/>);</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>After some time, upstream maintainers incorporate
  the provided translation in the package (or CVS) and the translation
  is considered "published". This is the final step for a translation,
  until the original translated item changes.</para></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>When the original item (document, wml or PO file) is modified, the cycle
  starts again. However, in that case, the last translator
  who worked on it is considered upstream's point of contact ((s)he
  should be contacted whenever there is a need to update the
  translation). The last translator is also typically considered as the
  maintainer for upstream's translations so there is no need to tell
  the translation team that (s)he will be updating the translation ((s)he is
  supposed to do it, as (s)he is in charge). Moreover, on many occasions,
  when the changes to the original item are few, there is not really a
  need to do a full review of the new translation by the translation
  team.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="pseudo_urls"><title>Pseudo-urls used by the robot</title>

  <para>A pseudo-url is made of the following:</para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
[&lt;state&gt;] &lt;type&gt;://&lt;package&gt;/&lt;file&gt;
</screen></informalexample>


  <para>These pseudo-urls are used in the mail Subject: to help the
  robot distinguish which mails need to be handled by it and which
  mails are part of the mailing list discussion.</para>

  <para>The contents of the pseudo-url are:</para>

  <variablelist>


  <varlistentry><term>state</term> <listitem><para>The state the
  translation is in, for more information see <xref
  linkend="pseudo_urls_state"/>.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>type</term> <listitem><para>The type of item
  being translated. The translation coordination robot accepts the
  following item as valid types in the pseudo-url to indicate a
  translatable item: po-debconf, debian-installer, po, man or wml
  (webwml is deprecated, wml should by used
  instead). </para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>package</term> <listitem><para>the name of the
  package where the document came from. www.debian.org is used for the
  wml files of the Debian web site
  cvs.</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>file</term> <listitem><para>the filename of the
  document, it can contain other information such as the path to the
  file or the section for a manpage, so no other document in the same
  package should be referred the
  same.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
 
  
 </variablelist>

 <para>The structure of name depends on the chosen type. In principle
 it's just an identifier, but it's strongly recommended to follow the
 following rules:</para>

 <itemizedlist>

 <listitem><para>po-debconf://package-name/language.po</para></listitem>

 <listitem><para>po://package-name/path-in-sourcepackage/filename.po</para></listitem>

 <listitem><para>debian-installer://package-name/path-in-sourcepackage</para></listitem>
  
 <listitem><para>wml://www.debian.org/address_of_page</para></listitem>

 <listitem><para>man://package-name/section/subject</para></listitem>

 </itemizedlist>


  <section id="pseudo_urls_state"><title>Translation states handled by the robot</title>

  <para>The translation coordination robot can track what stage is a
  translation for any item through the use of the following keys in
  the <quote>state</quote> part of the pseudo-url:</para>

  <variablelist>
 
  <varlistentry><term>TAF</term> <listitem><para>(<quote>Travail &Agrave;
 Faire</quote>, French for "translation to do", "taf" also means "work" in French slang) is sent to indicate that
 there is a document that needs to be worked on;
 </para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>ITT</term> <listitem><para>(Intent To Translate)
  indicates that there is a translator that is planning on working on
  a given translation. This helps preventing translators to duplicate their 
  work;</para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>RFR</term><listitem><para>(Request For Review) states than an initial translation is finished. The
  translator will attach the translation itself to the sent e-mail,
  for peer review. This key might be used more than once for the same
  item<footnote><para>Some translation robots use RFR2 for subsequent
  reviews</para></footnote> if substantial changes have been made to
  the initial translation based on other's comments. Just like with
  CVS commit e-mails, translators expect a reply to these requests
  even if it's just to say <quote>The translation is OK.</quote>;
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>


  <varlistentry><term>ITR</term> <listitem><para>(Intent To Review) a
  peer of the translation team notes that (s)he is working on a review of
  the translation and might take some (typically because the
  translation is large, or because the reviewer will not have time
  available until a given point in time) This is used to prevent the
  original translator to consider the translation as finished (send an
  LCFC, see below);  </para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>LCFC</term> <listitem><para>(Last Chance For
  Comments) tells the team that the translator considers the
  translation to be finished and has included the comments from the
  review process. (S)he is giving a last chance for peers to review
  before the translation is submitted upstream. Typically, it is sent
  when there are no no ITR's, discussion following the RFR has ended
  and it has been three days since the RFR was sent. Most translation
  teams don't allow translators to do this unless at least one member
  of the team has reviewed the translator's work;
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>BTS#&lt;bug number&gt;</term> <listitem><para>
 (Bug Tracking System) tells the team that a bug has been
 open to submit the translation to the maintainer. This is useful,
 since the translation robot can then automatically start checking if
 the bug report is still open and updates the translation status
 accordingly;</para></listitem></varlistentry>


  <varlistentry><term>FIX#&lt;bug number&gt;</term> <listitem><para>
  (bug FIXed) notes that an open bug has been fixed
  already (useful if the translation robot missed it being closed);
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>DONE</term> <listitem><para> states
  that the translation has been finished and is now included upstream. This should be used in cases where no bug report is involved such as web site translations. Otherwise, the robot will handle DONE automatically by crawling the Bug Tracking System;
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>HOLD</term> <listitem><para> put a
  translation on hold, when the original version has changed but there
  is no need to update the translation, e.g. the translator knows
  other modifications will be done soon on the translation and they
  don't want someone else to update it too quickly.
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

   </section> <!-- of translation states -->
  </section> <!-- of pseudo-urls -->

  <section><title>Example of translation robot usage</title>

  <para>This is a typical example of the way the translation robots are currently used.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
  
  <listitem><para>A translator (T) wants to work on the PO-debconf translation of the exim4 package, instead of just saying so in natural language in the mailing list. (S)he sends this:</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Subject: [ITT] po-debconf://exim4
</screen></informalexample>


  <para>The translation robot, when seeing that format in the mail's
  subject, processes the mail, retrieves the data (it is an ITT, of the
  po-debconf type, for the exim4 package, send by translator T on this
  date and time), stores it in a database. This information is
  presented whenever the translation status page is viewed (since it's
  driven by the database). The body of the mail is not processed, only
  the subject. </para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>Translator T completes the translation a few days later and wants people to review his/her work, so (s)he sends the following mail:</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Subject: [RFR] po-debconf://exim4
</screen></informalexample>


   <para>The file to review should be attached to the mail<footnote><para>Some
  translation robots don't handle compressed files but most will
  handle MIME attachments</para></footnote>. The robot processes this
  mail, notes the status change in the database and extracts the file
  from the mail. The web pages can be used to retrieve the file
  itself.</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>After some reviews, translator T sends a mail with an LCFC, attaching the file (which is, again, parsed by the robot) and after a few days sends the document to the BTS and sends this mail to the list:</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Subject: [BTS#123456] po-debconf://exim4
</screen></informalexample>


  <para>Once this is done, the translator's work is considered finished and the
  translation robot will, through a periodic job, review if the bug is
  closed in the bug tracking system. Whenever it is closed, it will be
  marked as DONE (and will be hidden from the view of the page after a
  month)</para> </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Throughout this process both members of the team subscribed to
  the list, new members which were not subscribed when the process
  started and the translation team coordinator have full access to the
  translation status (and its history) through the web application of
  the translation team robot.</para>


  </section><!-- of translation robot example -->

<!-- TODO: expand this ? -->
  <section><title>Future changes for translation robots</title>

  <para>In the future, the different translation robots of the
  translation teams should be merged into one common database as part
  of Debian's infrastructure for translators. This would help prevent
  having robots coded in different ways and help that new features
  (such as handling compressed translations or testing PO files with
  <command>msgfmt</command>) need to be coded in each of the
  independent robots.</para>

  </section>

  </section> <!-- of the translation robot -->


  </chapter>

  <chapter id="tools">
    <title>i18n/l10n tools in Debian</title>

<!-- TODO: More information on translation in the FLOSS world is 
      available at the 
      http://es.tldp.org/Articulos/0000otras/doc-traduccion-libre/doc-traduccion-libre/index.html (in spanish) -->

  <section id="generic_tools">
    <title>Generic tools: gettext</title>

      
     <para>In order to be able to internationalise the user
     environment the GNU project developed a set of tools which are
     known as <command>gettext</command>. These tools make use of the
     <command>locale</command> definition that is a part of the
     POSIX.2 standard and is implemented in the GNU
     <command>libc</command>. These definitions include the basic
     tasks of representing currency formats, date or numbers. But they
     also include the definitions of sorting tasks and the
     classification of codes based on the user's culture (such as the
     order of the letters in the alphabet). This aspect of a user's
     environment only needs to be defined once since these definitions,
     once covered, do not typically vary throughout time (except when
     fixing bugs or introducing new languages).</para>

     <para>The translation of messages according to the user's
     language in any given interface is, however, a more variable
     aspect of internationalisation of software. Not only messages
     that are shown to the user are translated usually, error
     messages, help of the options that the program use and any other
     message that a user might see at any point in time is suitable
     of translation.</para>

     <para>The <command>Gettext</command> tool was developed within
     the GNU project between 1994 and 1995 by a diverse group of
     programmers. This tool helps the creation of programs that can be
     distributed with multiple message catalogs in different
     languages. In localised environments the programs will choose the
     message catalog most suited to the environment as defined by the
     user and present messages in a given language.  </para>

     <para>This tool is almost transparent to the programmer. The
     programmer just has to mark in a special way messages that need
     to be translated. It is also transparent to the translator since
     the precise location of messages in the source code and the
     relocation of messages. Translators just have to keep the
     translation of a list of messages current. The gettext tools
     handle the creation of catalogues and their regeneration when the
     sources change but, at the same time, preserving translations
     already done.</para>

     <para>This way, the work of translating messages within a program
     is reduced to the task of doing an initial translation of all the
     messages and then the maintenance of the small (or big) changes
     introduced in the code that might have as a consequence the
     apparition (or change) of messages. The programmer has just to
     prepare the sources to use gettext through the use of the tools
     both in the program itself and in the tools that compile and
     build it (a process known as software internationalisation). Once
     this is done, the work of both groups can be done independently,
     which helps development both ways. That is, a translator does not
     have to depend on the programmer to introduce a new language and
     a programmer does not have to wait for the translators to do
     their job in order to publish a new release.</para>

      <para>More information is available in the <ulink
      url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gettext/gettext.html">official
      gettext project pages</ulink>. If gettext is already installed,
      online documentation is available that can be read executing
      <command>info gettext</command>.  </para>

      <para>Translation of messages using gettext is very simple.  A
      translator just needs to pick up a PO file either partially
      translated or completely untranslated and fill in the missing
      "gaps". Having many people with many different
      capabilities willing to cooperate makes it possible to
      collaborate without the need of in depth knowledge of the
      translation mechanism. This is how translation teams born. 
      Several front-end interfaces to gettext are available,
      such as <command>gtranslator</command>,
      <command>kbabel</command>, <command>poedit</command> or
      emacs'po-mode. One of consequences of the availability of the
      <command>gettext</command> tools is that it is not necessary to
      have programming knowledge to work on translation. The only
      requirements for working in translations are the knowledge of
      the original language, the language it will be translated to and
      the ability to edit .po files (with multiples tools being
      available to ease the task as described above).</para>

<sidebar>
<title>&dash; PO file example</title>
	<literallayout width="80">
# Copyright (C) 1999 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
# Javier Fernndez-Sanguino Pea&lt;jfs@computer.org&gt;, 1999.
#
#, fuzzy
msgid ""
msgstr ""
"Project-Id-Version: PACKAGE VERSION\n"
"POT-Creation-Date: 1999-06-21 14:21+0200\n"
"PO-Revision-Date: YEAR-MO-DA HO:MI+ZONE\n"
"Last-Translator: Javier Fernndez-Sanguino Pea &lt;jfs@computer.org&gt;\n"
"Language-Team: ES &lt;ES@li.org&gt;\n"
"MIME-Version: 1.0\n"
"Content-Type: text/plain; charset=CHARSET\n"
"Content-Transfer-Encoding: ENCODING\n"

#: hello.c:86
#, c-format
msgid "Usage: %s [-htvm] [--help] [--traditional] [--version] [--mail]\n"
msgstr "Modo de uso: %s [-htvm] [--help] [--traditional] [--version] [--mail]\n"
#: hello.c:148
msgid "This is GNU Hello, THE greeting printing program.\n"
msgstr "Este es Hola de GNU, EL programa que imprime un saludo.\n"

#
msgid "Translate this"
msgstr ""
</literallayout>
</sidebar>

      <para>The GNU project supports different groups of
      internationalisation. These groups are coordinated by a person
      in charge of the translation team.  There is no requirements,
      however, to provide constant dedication within a translation
      group. Translation can be a discrete effort. The existence of
      these groups, however, guarantees the revision of these discrete
      efforts from anonymous contributors (many time users). These
      groups are also in charge of developing glossaries to make
      translation of programs uniform and to maintain and update
      translations whenever new programs are published.</para>

      <para>This work is coordinated through the
      <emphasis>Translation Project</emphasis> at <ulink
      url="http://translationproject.org/"/>. The state of
      translations can be reviewed through a database of <ulink
      url="http://translationproject.org/domain/">translations</ulink> and
      <ulink url="http://translationproject.org/team/">translators</ulink>.
      </para>


  </section>

  <section id="wml">
    <title>Translation headers: wml</title>

<!-- FIXME: TBD -->
    <para>This section will be completed in further releases of this paper</para>

  </section>

  <section id="po4a">
    <title>Po for everything (po4a)</title>

<!-- TODO: 
     * Describe integration with Pootle?
       http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=9327343&amp;forum_id=43620

Translate Project: http://translationproject.org/
Pootle main site: http://pootle.wordforge.net/
Pootle list: translate-pootle@lists.sourceforge.net
Pootle list page: https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/
translate-pootle
-->

  <para><ulink url="http://po4a.alioth.debian.org/">po4a</ulink>
  (<emphasis>PO for anything</emphasis>) is a set of tools originally developed
  by Martin Quinson with the goal of easing translations and, more
  interestingly, maintenance of translations, through the use of
  gettext tools in areas where they were not expected, like
  documentation.</para>

  <para>Tools in the po4a package are used to update PO files from the
  original files and generates translated files from these PO files.
  </para>

  <para>The usual process is made of one initial step (convert
  translations to PO files) and two recurrent steps (update PO files
  and regenerate translated files).  </para>

    <section>
      <title>Converting existing/translated documentation to PO</title>

  <para>Converting documentation files to PO is the job of the
  <classname>po4a-gettextize</classname> command. When starting a new
  translation, <classname>po4a-gettextize</classname> will extract the
  translatable strings from the documentation file and write a POT
  file from it. When translated files exist, strings are grabbed from
  them and collected in a new PO file.
  </para>

  <para>
  The <classname>po4a-gettextize</classname> tool only extracts the Nth
  string from the translated file and matches it to the Nth string of
  the original file in the created PO file. It verifies that the original
  document and the translated documents have the same structure, but can't
  detect the state of the translation.  </para>

  <para>Because some manual expertise by translators is then required,
  all extracted strings are marked as "fuzzy" by the
  <classname>po4a-gettextize</classname> process.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Converting manpages to PO</title>

      <para>Converting existent manpages to PO files can be done using
      the <command>po4a-gettextize</command> tool:</para>

  <informalexample><screen>
$ po4a-gettextize -f man -m the_manpage -p foo.po
  </screen></informalexample>

     <para>Or if an existing translation exists:</para>

  <informalexample><screen>
$ po4a-gettextize -f man -m the_manpage -p foo.po -l existing_translation
  </screen></informalexample>

     <para>PO files can be converted back to manpages with:</para>

  <informalexample><screen>
$ po4a-translate -f man -m the_original_manpage -p the_PO_file -l translated_manpage
  </screen></informalexample>

  <para>Upstream authors can use the following Makefile to translate
  manpages by placing it in a <filename>po</filename> subdirectory
  under the documentation directory (which holds the manpages in troff
  format).</para>

<sidebar>
<title>&dash; po4a Makefile example</title>
	<literallayout width="80">
<![CDATA[  
PROJECT=project_name

# Sections of the manpages
SECS=1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8

PO4ATRANSLATE  = po4a-translate
PO4AUPDATEPO   = po4a-updatepo
PO4AGETTEXTIZE = po4a-gettextize

MAN1 = $(notdir $(basename $(wildcard ../*.1)))
MAN2 = $(notdir $(basename $(wildcard ../*.2)))
MAN3 = $(notdir $(basename $(wildcard ../*.3)))
MAN4 = $(notdir $(basename $(wildcard ../*.4)))
MAN5 = $(notdir $(basename $(wildcard ../*.5)))
MAN6 = $(notdir $(basename $(wildcard ../*.6)))
MAN7 = $(notdir $(basename $(wildcard ../*.7)))
MAN8 = $(notdir $(basename $(wildcard ../*.8)))

# List the languages the manpages are translated to
LANGS = fr
TRANS=$(foreach lang,$(LANGS),\
                  $(foreach sec,$(SECS),\
                            $(foreach man,$(MAN$(sec)),$(man).$(lang).$(sec))))

PARTIALPOT=$(foreach sec,$(SECS), $(foreach man,$(MAN$(sec)),$(man).$(sec).partial.pot))

all: $(TRANS)

#### CREATION OF THE POT FILE ####

$(PROJECT).doc.pot: $(PARTIALPOT)
        msgcat --use-first $^ -o $@

%.partial.pot: ../%
        $(PO4AGETTEXTIZE) -f man -m $< -p $@

#### CREATION OF THE POT FILE ####

$(PROJECT).doc.pot: $(PARTIALPOT)
        msgcat --use-first $^ -o $@

%.partial.pot: ../%
        $(PO4AGETTEXTIZE) -f man -m $< -p $@

#### TAKE CARE OF THE PO FILES ####

%.doc.po: $(PROJECT).doc.pot
        @echo -n "Merging $(PROJECT).doc.pot and $@: "
        @msgmerge $@ $(PROJECT).doc.pot -o $@.new
# Typically all that changes was a date. I'd prefer not to cvs commit such
# changes, so detect and ignore them.
        @if diff -q -I'#:' -I'POT-Creation-Date:' -I'PO-Revision-Date:' $@ $@.new >/dev/null; then \
          rm -f $@.new; \
          touch $@; \
        else \
          mv -f $@.new $@; \
        fi
        @msgfmt --statistics $@

#### MAKE THE TRANSLATIONS ####

# This is an example for French manpages, sections 1 and 8
# it needs to be modified 
%.fr.1: fr.doc.po
        $(PO4ATRANSLATE) -f man -m ../`echo $@ | sed -e 's/\.fr\././'` \
        -p $< -a $@.addendum -l $@

%.fr.8: fr.doc.po
        $(PO4ATRANSLATE) -f man -m ../`echo $@ | sed -e 's/\.fr\././'` \
        -p $< -a $@.addendum -l $@


#### MISC ####

clean:
        -rm -f $(foreach sec,$(SECS),*.$(sec)) *~ *.partial.pot


.PHONY: clean
.PRECIOUS: $(foreach lang,$(LANGS), $(lang).doc.po)
.INTERMEDIATE: $(PARTIALPOT)
]]>
</literallayout>

</sidebar>


  </section><!-- of converting manpages to PO4a -->

  <!--
  TODO
  This section could mention the supported formats: KernelHelp, Man, Pod, Sgml, Dia, LaTeX, Xml

  And tools similar to po4a (poxml, translate-toolkit (these ones are alredy
  mentioned in this document IIRC), gnome-doc-utils)

  -->

  </section><!-- of converting to PO4a -->

    <section id="po4a-for-doc">
      <title>Maintaining translated documentation with po4a</title>

  <para>The dataflow can be summarised as "master document --&gt; PO
  files --&gt; translations". Any changes to the master document will
  be reflected in the PO files, and all changes to the PO files
  (either manual or caused by the changes from the master document)
  will be reflected in translated documents.  </para>

  <para>Po4a tools allow defining a minimum translation ratio below
  which the translated document will not be generated anymore or will
  only contain the original strings. This avoids generating documents
  with too few translated strings but still allows the publication of
  complete translations. As a consequence, translated documents may
  still contain some strings in the original language. This tries to
  guarantee the accuracy of the translated document.</para>

  <para>This behaviour is a big improvement for documents such as
  manual pages. Indeed, an argument often used for not using these
  translations is the lack of guarantee that the translations are
  in sync with the original man pages. The po4a tools lower this
  argument, the price being sometimes mixed man pages, though.
  </para>

  </section> <!-- of po4a for doc -->

  <section>
      <title>Recommended po4a organisation for software</title>

      <para>This section is mostly taken from the <command>po4a</command>
      documentation and describes the recommended organisation for
      software that use <command>po4a</command>.</para>

      <para>A standardised architecture of the source tree will help
      the translation teams when they try to detect the POTs that need
      to be updated.  As a consequence, the following architecture is
      recommended:</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
  /
  /doc/
  /doc/en/
  /doc/en/
  /doc/po4a/
  /doc/po4a/add_&lt;ll&gt;/
  /doc/po4a/po4a.cfg
  /doc/po4a/po/
  /doc/po4a/po/&lt;pkg&gt;.pot
  /doc/po4a/po/&lt;ll&gt;.po
  /doc/&lt;ll&gt;/
</screen>
</informalexample>

    <para>Or, if you want to avoid a big POT and split it according to
    the packages, documents, formats, or subjects, you can use the
    following architecture:</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
  /
  /doc/
  /doc/en/
  /doc/en/
  /doc/po4a/
  /doc/po4a/add_&lt;ll&gt;/
  /doc/po4a/&lt;pkg1&gt;/po4a.cfg
  /doc/po4a/&lt;pkg1&gt;/po/
  /doc/po4a/&lt;pkg1&gt;/po/&lt;pkg1&gt;.pot
  /doc/po4a/&lt;pkg1&gt;/po/&lt;ll&gt;.po
  /doc/&lt;ll&gt;/
</screen>
</informalexample>

    <para>It is important to avoid a build failure if a
    translation cannot be generated (the PO is too outdated, an
    addendum cannot be applied, ...). Wildcards should therefore be
    used or tests be included to check whether the files are generated
    in the 'install' or 'dist' rules.</para>

    <para>When po4a is used upstream, it is recommended to run po4a in
    the 'dist' rule.  This will update the POT and POs, and will
    generate the translated documents.  </para>

    <para>These translated documents can be distributed in the source
    archive if the maintainer doesn't want to add a build dependency
    on po4a. This requires adding an autoconf check on po4a and will
    allow updating the documentation if po4a is available locally. If
    po4a is not available, documents will be distributed without being
    synced with the original version, but the build process won't
    fail.</para>

    <para>It is important to distribute the POT and POs in the source
    archive.</para>

    <para>When po4a is used in a distribution such as Debian, one
    should ensure that the source of the package contains only
    up-to-date POT and POs. This means that po4a should be run in the
    'clean' rule of the make process (typically in
    <command>debian/rules</command> for Debian packages.</para>


<informalexample>
<screen>
clean:
       # Update the POT and POs
       cd &lt;...&gt;/po4a &amp;&amp; po4a --no-translations --rm-backups &lt;package&gt;.cfg

build:
       # Generate the translations
       cd &lt;...&gt;/po4a &amp;&amp; po4a --rm-backups &lt;package&gt;.cfg
</screen>
</informalexample>


   </section><!-- of recommended organization -->

  </section> <!-- of po4a -->

  <section id="debconf-updatepo">
    <title>Debconf-updatepo and po-debconf tools</title>

    <para>Tools in the po-debconf package are mostly aimed for
    maintainers use.  The central tool is the debconf-updatepo
    utility. This utility should be run each time a change happens in
    debconf templates, i.e. most often the files names *.templates in
    the debian/ directory of the package source tree.</para>

    <para><command>debconf-updatepo</command> looks for all files
    listed in the <filename>debian/po/POTFILES.in</filename> and
    search in these files for translatable strings. Instructions on
    how to set a debconf string as translatable are given in the
    po-debconf(7) man page. This can be summarised as "just put an
    underscore character before the field names".</para>

    <para>All translatable strings are written by <command>debconf-updatepo</command> in a
    "template file" named <filename>debian/po/templates.pot</filename>. In the same time, all
    PO files that are present in <filename>debian/po</filename> are updated with regards of the
    new strings.</para>

    <para>Changed strings are marked <emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis> (thus
    keeping the old translation) or
    <emphasis>untranslated</emphasis>. In such case, the old
    translation is kept as <emphasis>obsolete</emphasis> entries et
    the end of the PO files.</para>

    <para>"fuzzy" strings translations are never used. When a debconf
    template includes more than one fuzzy string, the whole template
    will be shown untranslated to users.</para>

    <para>Maintainers should run <command>debconf-updatepo</command>
    as soon as they change templates. Some i18n maintainers recommend
    running it in the package clean target to ensure that all PO files
    AND the POT file are up-to-date. There is nothing worse than a
    package with obsolete files.  Some other maintainers rule against
    running <command>debconf-updatepo</command> in the clean target as this is likely to
    modify files in the debian/ directory.</para>

    <para>Rebuilding the templates file that will be shipped with the
    package, as of
    <filename>debian/&lt;package&gt;/DEBIAN/templates</filename> is
    the job of <command>po2debconf</command>. This utility is
    auto-magically called by <command>dh_installdebconf</command> for
    developers that use debhelper tools. This is actually a very good
    argument for using debhelper tools for packages that use debconf.</para>

    <para>The final templates file uses the encoding defined in
    <filename>debian/po/output</filename>. The default value is
    "utf8". It is highly recommended to use "utf8" in all cases. There
    is actually no good reason to use anything else. This will not
    affect the way the templates will be displayed, even in non UTF-8
    environments.</para>

    <section><title>The podebconf-report-po utility</title>

    <para>The <command>podebconf-report-po</command> utility is aimed
    to send notices about needed updates to all translators who have
    incomplete files (at least one fuzzy or untranslated string).</para>

    <para>Using it before planning an upload of a package with modified templates
    is strongly recommended. Translators do not really like to
    discover changes and needed updates after a package has been
    uploaded.</para>

    <para>When using this utility, maintainers should remember that
    many translation teams need time for their internal QA processes
    to take place. Leaving only a few days for translators to update
    their work, especially when important changes occurred, is nearly
    similar to a call for bad translations.</para>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="doc-check">
    <title>Documentation's doc-check</title>


  <para>Translation updates for documentation are handled through a
  script called <command>doc-check</command>. Although the tool shares
  a common name, different documents use a different version (or
  incarnation) of the same tool (or concept). Basically, the translators
  need to add to each translated file a translation header that
  specifies which file revision was translated. So, if a document was
  translated based on the 1.12 revision in CVS, a translator would add
  this header: </para>

  <informalexample><screen>
&lt;!-- CVS revision of original english document "1.12" --&gt;
  </screen></informalexample>

  <para>The specific header format used might vary between documents,
  for example, this is the translation header for the translation of a
  file in the Debian Installation Guide:
  </para>

  <informalexample><screen>
&lt;!-- original version: 12756 --&gt;
  </screen></informalexample>

  <para>If these headers are in place a translator can use the
  <command>doc-check</command> tool to:</para>

  <itemizedlist>

  <listitem><para>show which translated files have a different
  revision number from the original English files</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>show what changes have been made in the original
  English file</para></listitem>

  <listitem><para>help keep track of which files have not yet been
  translated</para></listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In order to use the tool the translator just needs to update
  his/her local copy of the document source code, run the script and
  review the output. The use of a revision control system helps the
  translator extract<footnote><para>The <command>doc-check</command>
  script of the <emphasis>d-i</emphasis> project can extract the
  changes between revisions by making the proper queries to the
  revision control system if asked to.</para></footnote> which changes
  have been introduced in the translated file. (S)he can then update the
  file, update the translation header and commit his/her changes.</para>

  <para>This mechanism is indeed very similar (if not the same) to the
  mechanism used in the website to manage translations.</para>

  <para>Translations that feel more comfortable using PO files can use
  either po4a (see <xref linkend="po4a-for-doc"/>), or
  <command>poxml</command>. The Debian Installer uses
  <command>poxml</command> and provides tools to convert from the XML
  files to PO files for the translation teams interested. A different
  set of tools converts the PO files back into XML files. "Out of
  dateness" of translations is handled through the same PO mechanisms
  (<emphasis>fuzzy</emphasis>) as those used by
  <command>gettext</command> to determine whether to show a translated
  message or not.</para>

  </section>


  <section id="l10n_bts">
    <title>Use of the BTS for translation work</title>

      <section>
	<title>Translators</title>

   <para>As always, using Debian Bug Tracking System to deal with translation work and particularly to send translation updates or new translations, is the recommended way.</para>

<para>Translators are encourage to send new translations or
translation updates as bug reports against the relevant package. The
use of the <command>reportbug</command> utility is encouraged for
translators working on Debian systems or Debian derivative systems
(such as Debian-Edu or Ubuntu). The <command>reportbug</command> is part of the <command>reportbug</command> package which can be installed with the following command line:</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
aptitude install reportbug
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
This should be done as root or, if the current user is listed in
<emphasis>sudoers</emphasis> by using the <command>sudo</command>
command (this is useful on Ubuntu systems where the root user is not
activated by default):
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
sudo aptitude install reportbug
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
Bug should be reported against the <emphasis>source</emphasis> package which the translation belongs to, preferably.
</para>

<para>
<command>reportbug</command> will prompt for a bug <emphasis>title</emphasis>. By general agreement, semi-formalised bug titles should be sued:
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
[INTL:&lt;code&gt;]: &lt;language&gt; &lt;type&gt; translation
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
where <emphasis>&lt;code&gt;</emphasis> is the language ISO-639 code, <emphasis>&lt;language&gt;</emphasis> is the language name in English and <emphasis>&lt;type&gt;</emphasis> is the type of translation (which can be "po-debdonf", "programs", "man pages", etc.)
</para>

<para>
<command>reportbug</command> will request for the bug severity to use. By general agreement in the project, the <emphasis>wishlist</emphasis> severity should be used.
</para>

<para>
<command>reportbug</command> will also prompt for <emphasis>bug tags</emphasis> which is a common way to categorise bug reports. The <emphasis>l10n</emphasis> and <emphasis>patch</emphasis> bug tags should be used.
</para>

<para>
<command>reportbug</command> then drops the user into a text editor to fill in the bug text. There is usually no need to be very verbose there as most informations are obvious.
</para>

<!-- TODO:
	Sometimes, when there are multiple PO in the package, it could be nice to
	specify which PO is updated (something like "debconf PO", or specifying the
	path: debian/po/fr.po).
-->

<para>
Finally, the translation file should be attached to the bug report
(<command>reportbug</command> is clever enough to warn users when a
bug tagged <emphasis>patch</emphasis> is sent without any file
attached. The attached translation file can be sent as is but several
translators commonly compress these files with <command>gzip</command>
to avoid maintainers mail user agent messing up with the file
encoding.
</para>

<para>
A recent announcement by Denis Barbier proposed to <ulink url="http://lists.debian.org/debian-i18n/2006/02/msg00013.html">use bugs usertagging to categorise l10n bugs</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
This proposal sets up user tags such as
<emphasis>l-&lt;code;&gt;</emphasis> where &lt;code;&gt; is the
language code, <emphasis>l-</emphasis> being a prefix for
<emphasis>language</emphasis> while <emphasis>t-</emphasis> could be a
prefix for <emphasis>territory</emphasis> (or country). The
<emphasis>user</emphasis> to use is
<emphasis>debian-i18n@lists.debian.org</emphasis>. This proposal is
currently not completely finalised and could change in the future.
</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Package maintainers</title>

<para>
Maintainers should use the sent files as is. They should NOT change
them and, for instance NOT re-encode them. It is recommended that
maintainers check that the translation is sent by someone who is
either the former translator or someone with his/her approval. When in
doubt, advice should be requested in the debian-i18n mailing list.
</para>

<para>
When maintainers receive new translations or translation updates for
an upstream program, they must send them to upstream and possibly
setup a good working method with their upstream for this translation
updates flow. The translations of software in Debian should
idealistically not be different from upstream translations.
</para>

<para>
Translation updates are registered exceptions to freezes that occur at
the end of the Debian release cycle, so maintainers should make use of
that general freeze time to make sure they have complete translations
and possibly request for updates to their translators.
</para>

      </section>
  </section>

  </chapter>


  <chapter id="other_projects">
    <title>Relationship with other projects</title>

<!-- FIXME: TBD -->
  <para>This section will be completed in further releases of this paper</para>

  <section id="translation_packaging">
    <title>Translation packaging</title>

<!-- FIXME: TBD -->
  <para>This section will be completed in further releases of this paper</para>

  </section>

  <section id="bug_reports_upstream">
    <title>Handling of bug reports for upstream translations</title>

<para>
The situation varies considerably between upstream projects which
have a strong and well organised upstream i18n/l10n team, such as
OpenOffice.org, KDE, Gnome and similar projects, or even "smaller"
projects where translations are handled through the Translation
Project, and other projects for which the localisation is mostly done
by direct interaction between the upstream maintainer and a variable
set of volunteers.
</para>

<para>
For the first kind of project, it is recommended that Debian
maintainers and translators avoid interfering with the upstream
i18n/l10n resources. This means that translation updates coming
through the Debian BTS should be redirected to the upstream i18n team,
or to the Translation Project. In short, sending translation updates
through the Debian BTS is here discouraged.
</para>

<para>
For projects where internationalisation and localisation is done
autonomously, Debian maintainers can interact more closely with
upstream. Most upstream maintainers may be deeply interested by the
big amount of Debian resources for localisation and it is recommended
to push for Debian translators to maintain as many upstream
translations as possible, for such projects.
</para>

<para>
This needs a closer interaction with the upstream maintainers, for
instance by requesting access to his/her revision control system or
have him/her deal directly with the Debian BTS (tagging and triaging
bugs). Such method has already proven to be a good method to develop a
general stronger interaction with upstream, not only for localisation.
</para>

  </section>


  <section id="lousy_translations">
    <title>Handling of errors in upstream translations</title>

<!-- FIXME: TBD -->
  <para>This section will be completed in further releases of this paper</para>

  </section>

  </chapter>

</book>

<!-- EOF -->
